I'm singing We Need You, and I'm carrying up like four things with two hands.
I should have asked for some help, but I told you, prone to wander.
Lord, I feel it.
Well, good morning, everyone.
Thank you so much for being here.
If we have not yet had the privilege of meeting, my name is Ryan, and I get the tremendous
honor of being one of the pastors here, and just the last couple weeks, we changed up
our early schedule, and we used to have a meeting at 945, and it kind of kept all of
us from getting out in the lobby and mingling, and the last couple weeks, I've been out, and
I've just been so reminded of how thankful I am for each one of you.
Our church is really incredible, and it's not because of anything we do.
It's because of the culture that you all are creating with one another, and so I'm so thankful
for each of you.
This is our fourth and final week, so if you have been struggling with the solitude practice,
if you have been muscling through sitting awkwardly in silence, hopefully by now you've had some
type of encouraging experience, but this is our last week as we look at solitude, part
of a larger series that we've talked about on the practices of Jesus, that Christianity is
not just about learning about Jesus, but it's about following his example, about becoming
like a person of Christ, offering our entire selves, not just our minds, but the Scriptures say to love
the Lord your God with all of your heart, soul, mind, and strength. It's our whole person that is being
invited to surrender to and conform to the image of Jesus, and we've said that solitude is
particularly important for our current cultural moment. We are constantly busy, distracted by all kinds of
things, and this is an invitation from Jesus to withdraw from all of the busyness and distraction
that our world offers, and to sit in silence apart from any outside agendas or noise, and just allow
the God of the universe who created us, who knit us together in our mother's womb, to speak to us.
And this series was intentionally planned, we said this last week, to lead into the season of Lent,
which is an invitation from the church throughout history to experience God in the desert, right, to give
up some things, to fast from some things, to get this extra space away from God. And so if you're
interested in participating in Lent, if it's new to you or not new to you, we'd love to invite you to one of
those Ash Wednesday services, either on your lunch break or in the evening on your way home. Or if you're
really brave, and you want to go to an actual high church service, I can give you some
recommendations. Ours will be a low church version of a high church service. But if you
if you really want to step out of your comfort zone and get some real liturgy, I can point you in the right
direction. Week one, we define solitude as a space for God apart from all inputs and agendas. Week two, we said
that solitude is a place where we encounter ourselves, that we become aware of what's actually going down in the
deepest part of us, that we often can, we can often push away and not actually experience. But in
solitude, these feelings of shame or guilt or regret or sinful habits, they come up and we become aware
of them. We become naked before a holy God. And it's in those spaces where we want to be affirmed of
God's grace and love for us. It's not a place of shame and guilt that we sit there, but it's it's that we
can get to a place like Genesis says, where we can be naked and unashamed for a holy God. Not because of
anything that we've done, but because of what Jesus has done for us. Last week, we said that solitude is a
place we become aware of how the enemy seeks to deceive us and distract us from living the lives that
God's called us to. And we're going to finish the series by talking about how solitude is a space
where we can encounter God, which really is the whole point, right? It's the whole point of all of
the practices, not just the solitude practice. It is the it is the point with that we come into
awareness of and relationship with the Father. And I would just caution you as we talk about practice
based discipleship. Every every good thing has a pendulum that can be swung. And what can happen in
practice based discipleship is it can be legalistic rules that we build into our life to make us feel
holy, but that aren't actually leading us to be transformed into a person. We can we can do these
actions for ourselves more than we can do them as a way to offer ourselves to God. And if you don't
believe me, just read the Gospels. There's this group called the Pharisees that a lot of people
probably know, right? And like, no, like, we have this propensity. They had daily, weekly, monthly,
quarterly. Their whole calendar was built around practices that were intended to offer themselves
before God, but rather they they twisted that. They took those practices and it allowed them to feel
holier than they actually were. It didn't actually accomplish the goal. And so today I hope to remind us
and and as we send ourselves out to continue to participate in solitude that if you're
not doing it to encounter the living God, then don't do it. It's legalism. This is an invitation
to the God who made you and love you. That's the direction we're headed. Let me pray and we'll get
started and I'll talk to you about why I have a child's toy on my table. Father in heaven, we are so
grateful for another day to spend in your presence, for another day to worship together with brothers and
sisters, for another day to invite people who are spiritually seeking you to come into our space
and to hear from you and to see you work in the midst of our community. God, we want to see your
kingdom come. We want to see your will be done on earth as it is now. And far more often we are
obstacles to that plan than we are assets. And so this morning, God, remind us of your purpose,
plan for our lives, of how it is that you bring your kingdom on earth. Allow us to render our will to do our
will for glory for our good and for the good of our neighbors. Amen. If you want to follow along with
me, I'm going to be in Mark chapter one. Mark chapter one is going to be our pastor for the day. And one of my
favorite things, one of my new favorite things, some of you might know, I became a father not too long
ago. My son's turning two here in a couple of months. And one of my new favorite things in the world is to
play with my son. It's hard to get him to do anything but play golf, which is probably my fault.
But I love playing golf with him, but it's fun when I can kind of break him away and get him to focus
on something else that does something other than just fine motor skills. Right now his fine motor skills
are fantastic. But like, let's like, you know, love the Lord your God with the heart, soul, mind,
strength. Let's work the brain a little bit. So this is one of my favorite toys that if I can get
him to break away from golf for a little bit and get him to play with this toy, it's a work truck
with shapes inside. Right. And then on the truck, there are different shapes cut out. And so the deal
is you pick up a wooden shape and you have to find where it goes and you get it inside the truck and
we all celebrate and everyone claps for Rory and Rory claps for himself. And it's fun, right?
The problem is this toy is probably slightly, he's not ready for it fully yet. So here's what Rory
gets. Rory understands the goal. He understands that the wooden blocks need to get inside the truck,
but he doesn't fully grasp the strategy. Right. So he's like, he's just grabbing a shape and trying
to shove it in whatever hole he can find first. He's like, I know the blocks need to get inside the
truck, but I don't have time to figure out which block goes where. And oftentimes he gets really
frustrated, throws the block, flips the truck and moves on, picks up his golf club. Right. It's like,
all right, this is too much for me right now. But sometimes he can stick with it a little bit.
And that's when he starts to use the shortcut, the cheat code, where he just opens up the back
of the truck and just shoves all the blocks in. And he's like, look at me. I did it. I accomplished
the goal. And I share this story with you because I think it's a helpful illustration for how Christians
in America often operate when it comes to God's kingdom. I think we understand the goal.
We know the Lord's Prayer, your kingdom come, your will be done on earth that is in heaven. We know
the great commission, go out and make disciples of all nations, baptizing them in the name of the
Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit. We know the goal. But I'm fearful that in our zeal to
accomplish the goal and in our discipleship of the culture around us, the wisdom of the world around
us, that we don't actually follow God's strategy for how to accomplish the goal. That we get frustrated
because God's strategy is often painstakingly slow. That God's strategy is often transforming us
from the inside out one day at a time. And we want to see results. We're Americans, by golly. We want to
see God's kingdom come now. And so we get in this frustrated moment where we know what we're supposed
to be accomplished, but we don't necessarily know how to accomplish it. And maybe if we push through
the frustration, we find shortcuts. Maybe we find shortcuts where we can force something that looks
like kingdom success, but not doing it in the way that God's inviting us.
And so what I want to do with the rest of our time today is I want to talk about how solitude is a
place. I think solitude is an invitation to a place where we can become not just aware of God's goal for
our lives, but also his strategy, where we can slow down long enough, where we can get away long enough,
where he can not only just embed in us the goal of following Jesus, but also the strategy by which we
are called to do it. Last week, we talked about these people called the desert fathers and mothers. Some of you've
heard of them before, and that they had coined this term, the unholy trinity, the world, the flesh, and the
devil. These are three kind of things that are at work leading God's people away from God's purpose and his plan for
their lives. And last week, we focused a lot on the devil, right? The enemy seeks to distract and deceive us. And this week,
I think what we're going to see is the other two unholy trinity members at work are a bit even more subtle. We don't even
realize that we swim in this culture of the world, right? The world is just the cultural ideology around us. We swim in it
every single day, and we don't even realize when we're being deformed out of the image of Jesus by the world around us. And then our
flesh, our sinful desires, our selfish desires often manipulate what God wants to do in us. So that's kind of the
direction we're headed for the rest of our time. We're going to pick up in Mark chapter one, where we're going to
pick up verse 14. And before we hop in, I do want to give some context about the gospel of Mark. Mark is the
shortest of the Gospels. It is fast-paced and action-packed. And so if you're new to the Bible, and you don't have a
whole lot of time, Mark is a great place to start. He just gets the job done. He gives us a good sense for
what Christ's hectic ministry schedule would have looked like. It's always immediately this, immediately
that. They went here, they went there, they went there. There's no fluff in the gospel of Mark. He teaches
powerful lessons subtly with just a few words at a time. You have to pay attention to some clues, or else you
might miss the point altogether. And one of Mark's primary emphasis in his gospel, if you read it all the way
through, and remember that you're meant to hear it, not just to study it. And so as you hear the gospel
of Mark read a couple of times, many scholars have pointed out that it seems like one of Mark's primary
points is to show you that pretty much everybody, including the disciples, missed what Jesus was
doing. It's a gospel of failure. It's a gospel of showing how even the people who were closest to Jesus,
who heard him teach the most, who saw him model his lifestyle the most, missed the point altogether.
And many scholars think that Peter was actually the source material for Mark,
which would check out, right? Peter, one of the closest disciples to Jesus, who had one of the biggest
failures with Jesus, writes, helps Mark articulate this gospel in such a way that's inviting people to see
there's a way to follow Jesus and miss the whole point. And it's an invitation to not follow the
examples of the disciples or of the crowds, but to now, after the death, burial, and resurrection of
Jesus, to look back at their story, to see the ways in which they failed, and it's an invitation for you
not to follow that example. Does that make sense? All right, so let's pick up with that context in mind.
Mark 1, starting in verse 14, after John was put in prison, Jesus went into Galilee proclaiming the
good news of God. He said this, the time has come. The kingdom of God has come near. Repent and believe
the good news. This is the story right after the story we talked about last week where Jesus was
tempted in the desert. In Mark's gospel, this is his next story. And when we read at, when we read after
John was put in prison, it's important that we think about what that means, because I often, when I'm
doing my Bible study, I miss clues all the time, which is pretty embarrassing, because I went to Bible
college. So I'm like, yeah, all right, so it's a time stamp, right? He's giving us a time stamp just so we
can put ourselves into when this story happened. But it's so much more than a time stamp. It's a clue
for us to understand the culture, the sense of the moment we're entering into. For us to understand
our narrative this morning, it's important that we realize how volatile this time was for the Jewish
people. They were living under Roman oppression, and the relationship between the Jews and the Romans
felt like a ticking time bomb. There was prophetic writings that made the Jews feel like it was very
close to the time in which the promised Messiah was going to come and free them from the Roman
oppression and establish his kingdom once and for all to put them in their rightful place as the people
group who would be a blessing to the rest of the world around them. This culture was very, you could
feel it in the air. Almost all the Jews at this time would have thought it's time for God to do what
he said he was going to do. It's time for him to restore our nation and make us a blessing to the
people around us. And these prophetic writings, all of these prophetic writings about the Messiah came
with a promise of a forerunner, a forerunner who would come in the spirit of Elijah and prepare the
way. And John the Baptist seemed to fit the mold perfectly. He announced that the time had come,
that the Messiah was on the way. And he did it so well that they killed him for it.
John's actions stirred up the anticipation for the Messiah even more. And so when we read this line
after John was put in prison, we've got to realize that the whole culture, the whole temperature of
the room for the Jewish people was, wow, is it time? Is the Messiah coming? And then Jesus gives them
exactly what they were waiting for. He says, the time has come. The kingdom has drawn near. Repent and believe
good news. So this is, Mark is giving the crowds everything that they want. The Messiah is here. John
the Baptist is the forerunner of the Messiah. He came in the spirit of Elijah and the Messiah has come.
And then the next few verses, Mark gives us Jesus calling his first few disciples. They leave their
nets. They drop their nets. We've heard this story. And they follow Jesus. And that might seem like a
crazy thing for people to do if we don't understand the temperature of the room. If these fishermen
actually thought there was a chance that Jesus was the Messiah, if they actually thought there was a
chance that he was the one they were waiting for, of course they would risk everything. Of course they
would leave their nets behind and follow after him. And so that's what we read after John was put in
prison. Jesus announced the kingdom. He calls his disciples. And then we pick it up in verse 21.
They went to Capernaum and when the Sabbath came, Jesus went into the synagogue and began to teach. I told you
Mark does not mess around with fluff. Straight into it. The people were amazed at his teaching because he taught
them as one who had authority, not as the teachers of the law. Just then a man in their synagogues who was
possessed by an impure spirit cried out, what do you want with us, Jesus of Nazareth? Have you come to destroy us?
I know who you are, the Holy One of God.
It goes on.
Be quiet, said Jesus sternly. Come out of him. The impure spirit shook violently and came out of this man with a streak.
These people were all so amazed that they asked each other, what is this?
A new teaching and with authority, he gives orders to impure spirits and they obey him.
News about him spread quickly over the whole region of Gallup.
Mark's next scene is Jesus' disciples entering the synagogue, the place the Jews would most openly be
discussing about their anticipation of the coming Messiah. And he begins to teach in a new way.
Not like any teacher they've ever heard before, he begins to speak almost as if he is speaking for God,
on behalf of God. He's not saying, this is what I think the law means when it says this.
He's saying, this is what God is saying, speaking, as if a teacher they've never heard before.
And then on top of that, a demon cries out in the middle of the church service.
I was nervous about that one.
And refers to Jesus using one of the most prominent titles of one of the most clearly messianic psalms
in all of the Jewish hymn book.
Psalm 16 is a very clear messianic hymn.
And the demon calls Jesus by the title that is used for the Holy One of God.
The demon acknowledges Jesus.
He commands it to come out.
And news begins to spread quickly.
We went from Jesus in the wilderness to John the Baptist is put in prison.
And everything begins to spiral out of control for the Jews.
Could this be the time the Messiah is coming?
Jesus announces the kingdom, calls a few disciples, begins to teach with authority in the synagogues.
A demon calls him by a messianic name.
Jesus casts out the demon.
And now you can understand why news about him is spreading throughout the region of Galilee.
I told you, it was fast-paced, action-packed.
Mark is quickly giving the people what they want.
Anticipation is building and the news begins to spread.
Verse 29.
As soon as they left the synagogue, they went in with James and John to the home of Simon and Andrew.
Simon's mother-in-law was in bed with the fever, and they immediately told Jesus about her.
So he went to her, took her hand, and helped her up.
The fever left her, and she began to wait on him.
That evening, after sunset, the people brought to Jesus all the sick and demon-possessed.
The whole town gathered at the door, and Jesus healed many who had various diseases.
He also drove out many demons, but he would not let the demons speak, because they knew who he was.
Snowball just continues to roll down the hill for Mark here.
It's picking up speed.
Remember, Jesus came straight out of his solitude.
In the Gospel of Mark, Jesus comes straight out of his 40-day solitude with Jesus into this fast-paced, ministry-action-oriented gospel.
He's healing sick people in front of the entire town, and everyone was thinking the same thing.
The time has come.
Him.
This is the time.
We're not even through the first chapter of Mark yet, and, like, the whole crowd is ready to go, right?
Like, let's do this thing.
The Messiah is here.
And this is where the story begins to take a subtle but important turn.
Verse 35, after all of that fast-paced ministry, after Jesus beginning to enter the synagogue and teach with authority,
after casting out demons and healing the sick in front of a whole crowd,
I'm going to give you a bottle of water.
I'm going to keep profiting.
Brian's working on it.
Profit.
We have a prophet in our midst.
All right.
After all of that, this is where we pick up.
Very early in the morning, while it was still dark,
Jesus got up and left the house, and he went off to a solitary place.
That's the same word for the desert, aremos, solitude.
He went and prayed.
Simon and his companions went to look for him, and when they found him, they exclaimed,
Everyone is looking for you.
Whew.
Demons.
You can almost hear it in the disciples' voices.
What are you doing out here alone with God?
There's a crowd back there waiting for you.
We're doing this thing.
The Messiah, it's time.
Right?
Jesus replied, I love this.
Let us go somewhere else.
To the nearby villages, so I can preach there also.
This is why I have come.
So he traveled throughout Galilee, preaching in their synagogues.
I don't want to miss this.
This is where the story begins to shift.
Up to this point, Jesus is doing everything exactly the way the crowds and his disciples were.
He's teaching with authority, casting out demons, and feeling sick, and he's gathering a mass to follow.
The disciples likely go to bed that night with excitement in their bones.
They've got the momentum.
They've got the crowd.
Their popularity is growing.
Let's keep this ship rolling, and at this pace, we will overthrow Rome in a few months and restore Israel to its rightful plan.
This is the culture of the people of God waiting for the Messiah, and the disciples get up with excitement in their bones to get to work only to find Jesus gone.
In this fast-paced narrative of ministry success, Jesus withdraws into the Eremos, the solitude, the desert place, to pray.
And this is the place where Jesus regularly goes to encounter the Heavenly Father and where the will and ways of God in heaven come into tension with the will and ways of the disciples.
There's this tension point in solitude with God where what the disciples and the crowds want come into tension with what Jesus and the Father.
There's a different strategy at play when we get away into the solitude and spend time with God than the strategy of the crowds in the world.
All the disciples come to Him pretty much angry.
Mark gives us some subtle clues that they are really dropping the ball here.
The term went to look for Him is a way that suggests aggressive undertones.
It can also be translated, they hunt Him down.
Right?
The disciples that have just started following Jesus not too long ago are hunting Him down to tell Him what He should and shouldn't be doing.
As He's alone with the Father in solitude and prayer.
The verb, this one's fun, the verb used for looking, Mark uses it six other times in the book of Mark.
And every time it's used, it's used with people who have negative intentions.
His family come looking for Him because they think He's nuts.
Pharisees are demanding or looking for a sign.
Sadducees are looking to put Him to death.
Mark is very clearly telling us that there is a division between what the disciples want for Jesus and for what Jesus wants for Him.
It's in the place of solitude where the strategy of the kingdom of God comes into tension.
Between what God's followers want and what God wants of His followers.
The disciples brush into Christ's time of solitude with confusion.
Why would you be alone in the desert when we've got a crowd of people ready for you to continue your messianic?
They were desperate for Him to be Messiah, for God's kingdom to come to earth.
They could only see it through their own lenses, which were influenced by the world and the flesh.
It was influenced by the cultural ideas of power and influence.
How do movements pick up steam?
They pick up steam with popularity, crowds.
They pick up steam by saying the right things to the right people in the right spaces.
It's very strategic, very intentional.
And the disciples want Jesus to operate with this type of wisdom.
Not only that, but they come to Him from a fleshly desire.
They want things to go their way so that they can become popular.
They were thinking, I'm giving up everything because I'm going to be one of the right-hand guys for the Messiah.
I'm going to be in on the ground floor.
I'm going to get all the benefits of being part of one of the most influential movements in human history.
They understood the goal.
But the strategy is significantly different from Jesus and from the disciples.
I'm proud.
And it's when Jesus enters solitude where these things become intention.
I love how Dr. Tim Gombas puts it.
It says, while Jesus' agenda, His goal, His purpose is to establish God's kingdom rule,
His method or His strategy is dramatically different.
The Son of God ushers in God's reign through suffering and through death.
And His ministry will fly in the face of cultural expectations.
The strategy by which God brings about His kingdom will fly in the face of the world and the flesh.
This difficult mission is the reason Jesus is in the desert to pray.
To bring His strategy in alignment with the will of the Father.
To get away from the pressures of the world and what they want for Him.
And to get with the Father.
To abide in the Eremos with the Father.
And to keep in step with His will and His way.
I love how John 6 puts it.
Jesus says, for I have come down from heaven not to do my will, but to do the will of Him who sent me.
Jesus is fully God and fully man.
There is probably part of the fully man in Him that says, the crowd thing sounds nice.
Right?
The momentum thing, the popularity thing, that sounds nice.
But it's in solitude where He continues to surrender His will to the Father's will.
He continues to do things the way the Father invites Him to do them.
As we will see throughout the rest of Christ's life, the will of the Father flies from the face of the will of the crowds and even His sight.
And this is why Jesus invites us in solitude to pray.
So that we can begin to encounter God and understand His will and His ways that are in opposition to our own.
Here's my main point.
That's what I would say.
Solitude is a place where we encounter God and actively surrender to His will and His will.
It's a place where we can begin to realize that what God is inviting us into might be a little bit different than how we would do it if we were in charge.
The life and example of Jesus shows us God's strategy for establishing His kingdom.
And it's far different than any worldly strategy for a successful movement.
1 Corinthians 3.
The cross is foolishness to those who are perishing.
But to us who are being saved, it is the very power of God.
A cross?
A bloody Messiah?
A suffering servant?
Makes no sense.
The crowds and the disciples wanted a powerful king on a war horse with a sword.
They got a humble servant on a donkey.
And it's in solitude with God where we allow Him to correct the ways in which we want to accomplish His purposes.
But we want to do it on our agenda.
At our pace.
With our desire.
And oftentimes, if we're not careful, we'll get so frustrated that we'll flip the lid and we'll begin to make shortcuts.
We'll begin to do ministry based on business principles of the world.
And yeah, we might see some fruitfulness at the beginning.
But if we're accomplishing God's purposes with the wisdom of the world and not the wisdom of the cross, that those purposes will not last.
They will not flourish.
The disciples wanted a conquering king.
They got a suffering servant.
And then one of my favorite new images in the Bible.
I've told you guys this before.
All transparency.
I have avoided the book of Revelation like the plague.
But I'm starting to dip my toes in the water.
And one of the most beautiful visions in the book of Revelation sums up this point so well.
It's the climax of this heavenly throne room vision.
It's all political language.
There's a throne room of God.
And there's a scroll with God's redemptive plan for creation written on it.
And it's sealed with seven seals.
And there's no one in heaven and on earth who is worthy to open the seal.
To break the seals and to open the scroll.
This is so political.
This is we are waiting for a powerful leader who can do the thing we've been waiting for God to do for us.
We're waiting for this powerful leader to come.
And John hears an angel tell him, don't worry.
Behold the lion, the lion from the tribe of Judah.
Now.
That makes sense.
A roaring lion.
It's time.
Powerful God is going to come and do the thing.
And then John looks to see what he thinks is going to be a powerful lion coming to do the thing that they've been waiting to do.
And instead of seeing a lion, he sees a little lamb as though it was slain.
And all of heaven rejoices.
Because that is the strategy by which God brings about his kingdom redemption plan.
It's not through power or control or through political affiliation.
It's not through voting in the right people to do the thing that you want them to do.
It's through laying down your life sacrificially with love.
It's through looking to Jesus.
Following his example.
The lamb who is able to break the seals and open the scroll.
God's strategy of his kingdom, of his building his kingdom purposes, stands in stark contrast to the wisdom of the world and to the desires of our flesh.
We don't want surrender.
We don't want sacrifice.
We want influence.
We want control.
We want to be on the winning team.
And in solitude, we have this invitation to withdraw from the world.
To withdraw from the desires of our flesh.
And to let God dictate what success looks like.
What his strategy actually is for accomplishing his purpose.
I think most of us in the room are like the disciples and the crowds.
We're desperate for God's kingdom to come.
We've seen him show up in our lives and in the lives of those around us.
But my concern is I'm afraid that the way in which we want to partner with him to see his work done is far more often based on our desires and worldly wisdom.
Than it is the cross.
The lamb who is.
We want to cultivate God's kingdom in partnership with political powers and a popular message that can gather crowds.
But what if Jesus is actually inviting us to pick up a cross and follow?
What if kingdom building actually means this church gets smaller and smaller because we get more and more serious about doing the thing that he's inviting us to do the way he's inviting us to do?
It's not a message that draws crowds if the crowds are wanting to live by the wisdom of the world.
But, for those who are being saved, it is the very power of God.
There's only one way.
Only one way I can properly get Rory to play with this story.
And it's if I can just get him to calm down enough to lock eyes on me.
And I hand him the shape and I spin the wheel right in front of him.
And I almost have to guide his hand to put the shape in the truck.
And I think that's a picture of what solitude can be for us.
Solitude can be a place where we can lock eyes with God, knowing what the goal is, fully knowing that we want to see his kingdom come and his will be done.
And instead of getting frustrated, taking shortcuts, solitude is an invitation for us to lock eyes with God and for him to show us how to go about accomplishing his purposes and his will come.
And the beauty of the truck for the kingdom of God is it's a much simpler strategy.
This truck has multiple shapes.
The kingdom of God truck has only one shape.
The shape of the cross.
The kingdom of God accomplishes its purposes through sacrificial love, through laying down our life for the sake of the gospel.
They're surrendering our rights, our power, our privileges to serve those who are struggling, who are in need.
And solitude is a place where we can go to encounter God and surrender to his will and his ways, even though they're usually in stark contrast to how we would prefer to do it.
I want to be...
We've got time.
I have a slide that says bonus content.
And usually when I have a slide that says bonus content, there's no chance of getting to the bonus content.
Let's do it.
You guys good?
You good?
Are you good?
All right.
That's what I needed to hear because you've been playing for a while.
Fingers might be hurt.
Here's where I want to caution us.
We have to be careful.
Because there are ways in which we can go into the desert and reinforce our misunderstandings about them.
We talked last week about how there's this temptation to redefine God in our own image.
And it's really easy to surrender to a God who thinks a lot like us, who acts a lot like us, who would do things the way that we would do them.
Surrendering is a lot easier when we create a God in our own.
At the time Jesus came, there were four main ideologies.
We could even, we could call it political parties for fun.
That's probably not the best comparison, but just so we are tracking.
And all four of them had a strategy for which they thought God was going to accomplish his purpose, his will on earth.
Two of them avoided the desert like the plague.
They stayed with the crowds and the popular message.
You guys have heard of these people.
It's the Pharisees and the Sadducees.
The Pharisees avoided solitude and they sought to advance God's kingdom through legislating morality.
They were going to hold people accountable to God's law and God would eventually bring his kingdom when they were able to get everybody to stop sinning.
When they were able to get everybody to do things the way that they wanted to do them.
The Sadducees avoided solitude and sought to advance God's kingdom through allegiance with political parties in Rome.
Any of that sound familiar to you?
Are there still people today in church who want to see God's kingdom purposes accomplished by legislating morale?
By forcing people to obey God's law?
Are there still people today that would like to partner with political powers?
To elect the right officials?
To accomplish God's purpose.
And I'm, it might sound like I'm going after one side rather than the other.
There are Sadducees, modern Sadducees today that are aligning themselves with the Republican Party and the Democratic Party.
And both of them are falling woefully short of what the goal of the kingdom of God is.
You will not successfully see God's kingdom come through partnering with political powers, the way of the cross.
Individuals sacrificially laying down their lives to serve others, encourage others, build others up.
That's how we will see the kingdom of God.
There's two other groups and they actually did withdraw to the Aramos, the solitude place.
The first group is the Essenes.
They withdrew to the desert because of the corruption and sin in the Roman culture.
The problem is they withdrew and then never went back into the world.
They never had a positive impact on the culture around them because they were hiding in the desert with God.
Good, again, good, good motivation.
Good, they understand the purpose.
They missed the strategy.
All four of these groups understood the goal and they missed the strategy.
The last group is the Zealots.
And they would actually use the Aramos, the desert, to radicalize people against political powers.
And they would come back into culture with violence.
So I say all of this, it sounds like a super bad history lesson done too quickly.
But I say all of this because I think all of this maps onto our culture.
I think there's a way in which we can avoid solitude and still miss the point of what God wants to do through his kingdom.
I think there's a way in which we can withdraw into solitude just to reaffirm the ideas that we already have
and not to be lovingly corrected by a father who loves us.
The way of Jesus is in opposition to all four of these approaches.
He doesn't get sucked into the wisdom of the crowds, obsessed with bringing the kingdom through power.
He doesn't retreat to the desert to avoid going to the cross or to become radicalized against his enemy.
Rather, he withdraws to the desert to stay in tune with the heart of the father
and goes back into the world with a new kind of power.
One that doesn't seek to legislate morality or dominate those under his authority,
but one that sacrificially lays down his life for those in need
and invites others to follow his example.
Solitude is a place where we encounter God and actively surrender to his will.
We're going to do something real weird.
We're going to end our series on silence and solitude with some silence.
Not really solitude because there's a lot of us in here.
And if any of you have tried to participate in silence and solitude the past three to four weeks,
you probably know that this is a challenging thing, right?
But I think it's in the challenge that we're giving God space to do what only God can do.
So I'm going to pull a chair up so that I can be with you in silence.
I brought old school matches because it changes, you know?
I'm going to light a candle that is a physical representation of God's presence in the room.
God is here.
He is with us.
We cannot see him.
But we are silly people who need visible representations and reminders.
And so we light this candle to remind ourselves that God is in the room.
You'll notice that this candle is very low.
This is the Miller's candle for God's presence in silence and solitude.
And it is not very low because I am great at silence and solitude.
It is very low because my wife is great at silence and solitude.
I just wanted to set the record straight here.
I'm not trying to humbly brag here by showing you this much time, the Lord.
We're going to light this candle.
I'm going to sit down.
David's going to quit playing.
We're going to take a few deep breaths.
We're going to sit in silence and we're just going to listen.
We're going to invite God to do what he wants to do with this time.
And when I feel like it's been awkwardly long enough or when I hear kids shrieking from the
back, we'll stand up and we'll dismiss with the Lord's Prayer.
And so I'd invite you, if you want to close your eyes, that helps you.
That's great.
If you want to look at the flame, remind yourself that God's presence is here in the room.
Anybody just take a couple big, deep breaths, inhale and exhale, like you've just finished
a run and you're trying to fill yourself with the oxygen that you need to recover?
People use silence in different ways.
Maybe you just try and empty yourself of everything and wait for God to do something.
Maybe you bring an image to your mind.
As I was thinking about leading us, I was thinking about different images of the gospel that
we might bring to mind to reflect on.
The image of Zacchaeus in a tree, Jesus at the bottom saying, come have dinner with me.
The woman at the well, the woman caught in idolatry, the rich young ruler, the prodigal son or
the brother in the outside.
Maybe you bring to mind Mary outside of Lazarus' tomb.
Jesus weeping with her over the brokenness of the world.
I don't know what God wants to do with you or through you in this time of silence, but let's
just give it to him and see what he wants to do.
Jesus weeping with him and see what he wants to do with you in this time of silence, but let's just give it to him and see what he wants to do with you.
I don't know what he wants to do, but let's just give it to him and see what he wants to do with you.
I don't know what he wants to do with me, but let's just give it to him and see what he wants to do with you.
I don't know what he wants to do with you.
I don't know what he wants to do with you, but let's just give it to him and see what he wants to do with you.
I don't know what he wants to do with you, but I don't know what he wants to do with you.
I don't know what he wants to do with you.
I don't know what he wants to do with you, but let's just give it to him and see what he wants to do with you, but let's just give it to him and see what he wants to do with you.
I don't know what he wants to do with you, but let's just give it to him and see what he wants to do with you.
I don't know what he wants to do with you.
I don't know what he wants to do with you, but let's just give it to him and see what he wants to do with him and see what he wants to do with him and see what he wants to do with him and see what he wants to do with him and see what he wants to do with him and see what he wants to do with you.
I don't know.
Thank you.
My prayer for each and every one of us.
is that solitude could become an invitation that we would say yes to where we can lock eyes with the Father who loves us and we can surrender to his will and his way, his strategy for how he wants to do.
That we'd realize that even though it might feel like death in the moment to do the thing, the hard thing that we know Jesus is inviting us to do, that it actually leads to life more abundantly.
I invite you to stand with us.
Whatever version of the Lord's Prayer you know, feel free to say I put a version on the screen for those of you that don't know it.
Let's end our service today.
Let's end our service today by praying the prayer that Jesus gave his kingdom people for what it's like to live in his kingdom on earth until he comes.
Who art in heaven, holy is in your kingdom come,
who will be done on earth.
Give us day or day of bread.
Please forgive those.
Lead us not to temptation.
Deliver us from doors.
Go in peace, church.
Very proud of you.
That was discipline style.
Thank you.